<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Resumos xmlns:xsd="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA001</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Identification of potential biomarkers in whole saliva of cystic fibrosis patients using proteomic approaches</Titulo>
		<Autores> Lepesqueur LSS*, Tanaka MH, Lima GMG, Koga-Ito CY, Siqueira WL</Autores>
		<Universidade>Biopatologia Bucal - INSTITUTO DE CIÊNCIA E TECNOLOGIA / ICT-UNESP-SJC.</Universidade>
		<Email>lalepesqueur@hotmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>To investigate potential biomarkers for cystic fibrosis (CF) in human whole saliva (WS). Our hypothesis is that the identification of salivary biomarkers for cystic fibrosis could be used as an additional diagnostic tool in clinical setting. Seventy-eight patients aged from 6 to 20 years old were divided into 6 groups: patients with CF (G1, G2, G4, G5) were separated according to their age and disease severity, age- and gender-paired controls (G3 and G6). Samples of stimulated WS were collected and preserved at -80°C until processing. Salivary proteome profiles were obtained by liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry analyses. A total of 3070 unique proteins were identified in our analyses, 1619 proteins were found exclusively in CF groups. The profiles obtained for CF patients were compared searching for potential biomarkers common in all CF groups, resulting in 7 proteins. Some of these proteins have already been related to inflammatory and lung diseases such as Interleukin-16, CKLF-like MARVEL and MUC-3B. The pathogenesis of lung disease in CF populations may be involved with mucin hypersecretion and the mucus stasis. Regardless, the Mucin-5AC responsible for forming the mucus layers in airways was found in all 6 groups. Based on our bioinformatic analysis, MUC-3B was included in the panel of potential CF biomarker in saliva.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>In conclusion, proteomic technologies used for identification of salivary protein profiles emerge as a promising tool for diagnosis or monitoring of patients with CF.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPESP - 2018/02725-6</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA002</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Salivary diagnosis of Zika Virus using ATR-FTIR-spectroscopy</Titulo>
		<Autores> Oliveira SW*, Sousa LC, Georjutti RP, Siqueira WL, Goulart LR, Silva S, Jardim ACG, Sabino-Silva R</Autores>
		<Universidade>Faculdade de Odontologia - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE UBERLÂNDIA.</Universidade>
		<Email>stephaniewutke21@gmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>Zika Virus (ZIKV) diagnosis is performed by an invasive, painful and costly procedure. Consequently, the search for a more cost-effective (reagent free), non-invasive and specific method for ZIKV diagnosis is of great appeal, mainly due to ZIKV outbreak and its devastating consequences, particularly in pregnant women. Fourier-transform infrared (ATR-FTIR) spectroscopy is used in diseases diagnosis, however, applications in viral diseases are limited. To examine this, we intradermally challenged interferon-gamma gene knockout C57/BL6 mice with ZIKV (50 µl,10 5 FFU, n=7) or vehicle (50 µl, n=7). Samples were collected at day 3 (due to the peak of viremia) and spleen were also harvested. The changes in salivary spectral profile were analyzed by t test (p&lt;0.05) and the diagnostic capacity by ROC curve. The ZIKV infection was confirmed by real time PCR in spleen sample. Seventeen vibrational modes of saliva were detected in both control and ZIKV animals; and from these, 3 vibrational modes were pre-validated as potential biomarkers for diagnosis by the ROC curve. Compared to control, the 1547, 1597, and 2241 cm-1 vibrational modes of ZIKV animals presented a sensitivity of 100, 86, 86% and specificity of 75, 75, 88% (p &lt;0.001), respectively. Principal component (PCA) and hierarchical clusters (HCA) analysis also revealed high discrimination (p&lt;0.05) of ZIKV samples.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Our results suggest that ATR-FTIR applied to saliva might have high sensitivity and specificity in ZIKV diagnosis with potential as a non-invasive and cost-effective diagnostic tool.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: CAPES - 14/2016</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA003</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Low-cost glass ionomer cements hamper the performance of occlusal ART restorations - 2y survival and economic analysis of a RCT</Titulo>
		<Autores> Costa ICO*, Ladewig NM, Braga MM, Bonifácio CC, Mendes FM, Raggio DP</Autores>
		<Universidade>Ortodontia e Odontopediatria - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - SÃO PAULO.</Universidade>
		<Email>isabel_olegario@hotmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>The aim of this clinical trial was to evaluate the 2-year survival rate and cost-analysis of Atraumatic Restorative Treatment (ART) restorations using three different glass ionomer cements (GICs) for occlusal restorations in primary molars. After trial registration (NCT02377297) and ethical approval (#569,123), a total of 150 4-8 y old children were randomly allocated and treated on a school setting using Fuji IX (GC Corp), Vitro Molar (nova DFL) or Maxxion R (FGM), following ART premises. Materials and professionals costs were measured in Brazilian real (1,0 R$≅0.3USD) and considered to analyze baseline costs, while an estimation was done for treatments' incremental cost. Restoration survival was evaluated using Kaplan-Meier survival analysis, while Cox regression was used for testing association with clinical factors and Bootstrap regression (1000 repetitions) was used to perform a cost-analysis (α = 5%). The overall 2-year survival rate was 53% (Fuji IX = 72.7%; Vitro Molar =46.5%; Maxxion R=39.6%). Restorations performed with Vitro Molar and Maxxion R are more likely to fail when compared to Fuji IX. Considering the baseline cost, Fuji IX was the more expensive option (p&lt;0.001) (Fuji IX = R$18.7; Vitro Molar =R$14.6; Maxxion R=R$13.5). However, considering the simulation of incremental cost caused by failures until 2-year evaluation, no difference was found between the groups.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>After 2 years, restorations performed with Fuji IX proved to be superior in terms of survival and with a similar cost when compared to other low-cost glass ionomers cements.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: CAPES</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA004</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Three-dimensional maxillary, mandible and cranial base morphology evaluation of patients with unilateral cleft lip and palate</Titulo>
		<Autores> Villoria EM*, Souki BQ, Antunes FL, Assis MAL, Andrade-Júnior I, Oliveira DD, Soares RV</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia - PONTIFÍCIA UNIVERSIDADE CATÓLICA DE MINAS GERAIS.</Universidade>
		<Email>d.villoria82@yahoo.com.br</Email>
		<Resumo>The present study evaluated the pattern of maxillary, mandibular and cranial base morphology of patients with unilateral cleft lip and palate (UCLP), and compares it to patients without CLP (WCLP). The sample consisted of cone beam computed tomography of 124 patients (52 UCLP; 72 WCLP). Multiplanar identification of the landmarks S, Ba, N, ANS, PNS, A, B, Pog, Gn, Me, Po (right and left), Cd (right and left) and Go (right and left) was performed with ITK-Snap 2.2. Virtual surface models of the landmark were analyzed (3D Slicer CMF 3.0 software), to measure the 3D Euclidean distances and the X (right-left), Y (anterior-posterior) and Z (superior-inferior) components. Pitch rotation was also evaluated. The Student's T test (significance of 5%) was used. Seventeen measurements of UCLP showed significant differences relative to WCLP. These results suggest smaller development of the cranial base (A), smaller upper anterior facial height (B), more obtuse gonial angle (C) and more posteriorly positioned maxilla (D) in UCLP. Comparison of gender between UCLP and WCLP revealed that both UCLP genders presented A, B and C, and that females also presented D and a lower angle of the cranial base. Comparison of the cervical vertebra maturation staging between UCLP and WCLP, revealed that both pre-pubertal and pubertal UCLP presented A, B and C, and that pubertal also presented D.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Therefore, UCLP patients showed a distinct pattern in the maxillary, mandibular and cranial base morphology. These skeletal limitations should direct professionals to more pragmatic treatment decisions.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: CAPES - 001</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA005</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Genotoxicity and apoptosis of human gingival fibroblast treated with extracts of endodontic sealers incorporated with silver vanadate</Titulo>
		<Autores> Teixeira ABV*, Moreira NCS, S.takahashi C, Reis AC</Autores>
		<Universidade>Materiais Dentários e Prótese - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - RIBEIRÃO PRETO.</Universidade>
		<Email>ana.beatriz.teixeira@usp.br</Email>
		<Resumo>This study incorporated the nanostructured silver vanadate decorated with silver nanoparticles (AgVO<i>3</i>) into endodontic sealers and evaluated the genotoxicity and apoptosis of human gingival fibroblast (HGF). The AgVO<i>3</i> was incorporated at sealers AH Plus and Sealer 26 at concentrations 0%, 2.5%, 5% and 10%, and after setting of sealers, extracts of the specimens were obtained in culture medium DMEM e HAM F10 by 24 h and 7 days. FGH were grown, the genotoxicity was evaluated by the comet assay, and apoptosis, by the cell death assay. Cells were treated with culture medium (negative control), 300 and 500 μM methylmethanesulfonate (positive control - comet and apoptosis, respectively) and extracts from the specimens (n=3). After the treatment, the cells were collected and submitted to the comet assay and analyzed in the software Comet Assay IV. For apoptosis, after treatment and 96 h in the culture medium, the cells were collected and the Guava Nexin reagent was added for 30 min. Viable, apoptotic and necrotic cells were evaluated on flow cytometry. Data were analyzed by ANOVA and Tukey (α=0.05). The comet and cell death assay showed that there was no statistical difference between the negative control and the experimental groups (p&lt;0.05), except for the AH Plus incorporated with 10% of AgVO<i>3</i> with 7-days extract, which presented greater induction of apoptotic cells in relation to the negative control (p&lt;0.05).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>It was concluded that the incorporation of AgVO<i>3</i> into endodontic sealers does not induce DNA damage and FGH apoptosis, except for AH Plus 10% (7-days extract).</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP - 2017/04667-0</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA006</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Bioinspired Catechol Chemistry for Dentin Remineralization: A new approach for the treatment of Dentin Hypersensitivity</Titulo>
		<Autores> Lima JFM*, Mainardi MCAJ, Puppin-Rontani RM, Rodrigues Filho UP, Liporoni PCS, Calegaro ML, Rischka K, Aguiar FHB</Autores>
		<Universidade>Dentística - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Email>jcinhafml@hotmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>Dentin remineralization is of considerable clinical interest for dentin hypersensitivity (DH) and developing biomimetic analogs that can regulate hydroxyapatite (HAp) nucleation and growth remains a challenge. This study aimed to evaluate <i>in vitro</i> the potential for dentin remineralization using the following prepared poly(catechols): poly(dopamine), poly(DOPA), poly(caffeic acid) and a synthesized DOPA-peptide possessing collagen and calcium-binding domains (DOPA-Ahx-(Gly)<i>3</i>-(Glu)<i>5</i>). Dentin samples were etched with 37% of phosphoric acid for 2 min. Then, they were immersed in a freshly prepared phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) solution containing the respective catechol and laccase. After the reaction, they were immersed in calcium and phosphate remineralization solution, which was changed every day for 10 days. Samples of intact and demineralized dentin were used as control groups and kept in deionized water under the same experimental conditions. The remineralization precipitations were characterized by scanning electron microscopy, energy dispersion X-ray spectroscopy and X-ray diffraction. The application of different poly(catechols) and DOPA-peptide promoted crystal nucleation and the formation of HAp similar to intact dentin, which covered both the dentin surface and dentinal tubules walls.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Polymers consisting of catechol groups showed the ability to modify demineralized dentin surface properties, promoting mineral formation. The use of poly(catechols) may be encouraged for the development of a therapeutic technique for DH.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: CNPq - 132749/2018-1</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA007</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Endodontic sealers incorporated with a new silver base nanomaterial: cytotoxicity and release of metallic ions</Titulo>
		<Autores> Botelho AL*, Teixeira ABV, Castro DT, Reis AC</Autores>
		<Universidade>Materiais Dentários - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - RIBEIRÃO PRETO.</Universidade>
		<Email>botelho_andre@hotmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>This study evaluated the cell viability of human gingival fibroblasts (HGF) and the release of silver and vanadium ions of three endodontic sealers incorporated with nanostructured silver vanadate decorated with silver nanoparticles (AgVO<i>3</i>). The AgVO<i>3</i> was incorporated into the AH Plus, Sealer 26, and Endomethasone N sealers (0, 2.5, 5, and 10%) and extracts of the specimens were obtained in DMEM culture medium for 24 h. Cell viability was assessed 24 h, 7 and 14 days after cell exposure to the extracts by MTT assay. Silver (Ag<i>+</i>) and vanadium (V<i>4+</i>/V<i>5+</i>) ions release in distilled water for 24 hours was quantified by inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry. Data were analyzed by Kruskal-Wallis and Dunn's post-test (α=0.05). The incorporation of AgVO<i>3</i> to Sealer 26 and Endomethasone N did not influence cell viability of HGF comparing the 0% and modified groups (p&gt;0.05), but reduced cell viability of AH Plus (p&lt;0.05). Treatment time reduced cell viability. The release of Ag<i>+</i> and V<i>4+</i>/V<i>5+</i> was proportional to the concentration of AgVO<i>3</i>. AH Plus released more Ag<i>+</i> ions, and Sealer 26 and Endomethasone N release more V<i>4+</i>/V<i>5+</i>ions.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>In conclusion, the incorporation of AgVO<i>3</i> did not influence the viability of HGF of Sealer 26 and Endomethasone N sealers, and reduced the viability of the AH Plus, being inversely proportional to the time of treatment. The release of silver and vanadium ions was proportional to the concentration of the incorporated AgVO<i>3</i>.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPs - FAPESP - 2017/04667-0</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA008</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Do resin cements benefit from receiving additional violet light through ceramic?</Titulo>
		<Autores> Braga SSL*, Price RBT, Juckes S, Sullivan B, Soares CJ</Autores>
		<Universidade>UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE UBERLÂNDIA.</Universidade>
		<Email>braga.stella@gmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>This study evaluated the effect of delivering just violet, just blue, or a combination of violet and blue light from a polywave light curing unit (LCU) through ceramic on the degree of conversion (DC) of two resin cements that use different photoinitiators. A Bluephase Style curing light attached directly to a DC power supply delivered just violet (385-420 nm) or just blue (420-515 nm) light, and an unmodified Bluephase Style (BS) (385-515 nm) light was used to emit both wavelengths at the same time. The current to the LCU was adjusted to match the BS power values at both wavelength ranges and the power output was checked before and after DC tests using an integrating sphere attached to a fiber-optic spectrometer (OceanOptics). In all conditions tested, Variolink Esthetic LC neutral (VE) and RelyX Veneer translucent (RV) resin cements were light cured for 10 seconds through different thicknesses of glazed IPS e.max CAD low translucency A2 shade (0, 0.5 and 1.5 mm thick). DC was monitored using Fourier-Transform Infrared spectroscopy (Vertex 70) for 5 minutes. Data were subject to one-way, two-way and three-way analyses of variance (α=.05). The composites, thicknesses, and wavelengths all had a significant effect (p&lt;.0001). Increasing the ceramic thickness decreased DC. The DC of RV was significantly lower when just violet light was used. Both resin cements had higher DC when just blue or when the polywave light was used.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>A polywave light is not required to cure VE, and RV does not benefit from receiving additional violet light.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: PDSE-CAPES and Dalhousie Faculty of Dentistry Research Fund - 88881.189639/2018-01</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA009</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Influence of the concentration and type of functionalization of TiO2 nanostructures on the properties of experimental resins</Titulo>
		<Autores> Guimarães GMF*, Bronze-Uhle ES, Lisboa Filho PN, Pfeifer CSC, Gonzaga CC, Bombonatti JFS, Furuse AY</Autores>
		<Universidade>Dentística - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - BAURU.</Universidade>
		<Email>genine.guimaraes@usp.br</Email>
		<Resumo>This study evaluated the influence of different concentrations of functionalized TiO<i>2</i> nanostructures of an experimental resin. TiO<i>2</i> nanotubes (NT) and nanoparticles (NP) were synthesized and functionalized using 3-(aminopropyl)triethoxysilane (APTMS) and 3-(trimethoxysilyl)propyl methacrylate (TSMPM). TiO<i>2</i> nanostructures were characterized by x-ray diffractometer, EDS, zeta potential and TEM. Bis-GMA/TEGDMA resin mixtures were prepared and divided according to TiO<i>2 </i>nanostructure (NT and NP), concentration (0.3% and 0.9%), and functionalization (APTMS and TSMPM). Ninety-one resin discs were made (n = 7) and photoactivated. The degree of conversion (DC) was evaluated immediately and after 24 hours, and Knoop hardness (KHN) was evaluated after 7 days and after softening in ethanol 100%. Data were analyzed with one-way repeated measures ANOVA and Tukey's HSD (α = 0.05).For DC, there was a significant difference between resins (p &lt; 0.001) and times (p &lt; 0.001). For KHN, significant differences were found between resins (p &lt; 0.001) and after softening in ethanol (p &lt; 0.001). The resins × hardness interaction was significant (p &lt; 0.001). The highest values of DC were found for the groups with TiO<i>2</i> NT 0.3% functionalized with TSMPM (93%). The same favourable results were also observed for the hardness after ethanol immersion. The TiO<i>2</i> NT showed better results TiO<i>2</i> NP.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>TiO<i>2</i> NT showed excellent results regarding DC and hardness compared to TiO<i>2</i> NP. Funcitionaliz<i><i></i></i>ation by TSMPM showed better overall results than the conventional compound (APTMS).</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPESP - 2017/23331-3</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA010</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Tooth minimal wear for monolithic ceramic posterior crowns: effect on the biomechanical behavior, reliability and translucency</Titulo>
		<Autores> Dal-Piva AMO*, Tribst JPM, Jalkh EBB, Anami LC, Bonfante EA, Bottino MA</Autores>
		<Universidade>Materiais Odontológicos e Prótese - INSTITUTO DE CIÊNCIA E TECNOLOGIA / ICT-UNESP-SJC.</Universidade>
		<Email>amodalpiva@gmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>Despite monolithic crowns utilization increase, their performance has yet to be determined when tooth minimal wear (TMW) principle is considered. To evaluate the effect of TMW on the monolithic crowns performance, dentin analogues were machinned at two preparations (0.5 mm of difference) to receive first molar crowns. 126 crowns were divided (n=21/gr) according to the material (High translucency zirconia -YZHT, Lithium silicate reinforced by zirconia - ZLS and Hybrid ceramic -HC) and thickness (0.5 or 1 mm). Stress concentration was calculated using finite element method. The crowns were adhesivelly cemented and step stress fatigued (3:2:1) to calculate reliability for missions at 600 and 900 N at 50,000 and 10,000 cycles. Translucency was analyzed in 10 samples of each material and thickness. Higher tensile stress concentration was found in thinner and stiffer crowns. YZHT crowns were suspended when fatigue reached 1,500N load, thus 1-parameter Weibull was used to analyse the data. Reliability was only influenced at 900 N, by thickness. ZLS.5 showed similar survival than HC.5 that was similar to the groups that survived 100%. HC.5 showed 5x higher reliability than ZLS.5 and 6x than YZHT.5. YZHT showed high strength but low confiability. ZLS1 (22.3 ± 1.4)<i>A</i> presented higher translucency than HC1 (19.2 ± 0.6)<i>B</i> and YZHT1 (12 ± 2.9)<i>C</i>, whereas, ZLS.5 and HC.5 were similar (26.5 ± 2.3, 26.7 ± 2.2)<i>A</i> and superior than YZHT.5 (12.7 ± 1.2)<i>B</i>.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>HC.5 associates high reliability and translucency with low stress concentration, yielding better crown performance and tooth preservation.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPs - Fapesp - 2017/11535-3 and 2017/23059-1</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA011</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Post-extraction socket healing in subjects with chronic kidney failure undergoing hemodialysis</Titulo>
		<Autores> Andrade NS*, Caliento R, Sarmento DJS, Zambrana JRM, Figueiredo M, Costa C, Ortega KL, Gallottini MHC</Autores>
		<Universidade>Estomatologia - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - SÃO PAULO.</Universidade>
		<Email>natalia642@gmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>This prospective study assessed the post-extraction socket healing in individuals with chronic kidney failure (CKF) undergoing hemodialysis (HD), compared to non-CKF subjects, regarding the presence of postoperative complications and repair chronology. Thus, 48 individuals with CKF in HD comprised the SG (study group) and 29 individuals without CKF, the CG (control group). Two researchers compiled data from medical history, conducted a clinical examination, requested lab tests, and performed exodontia of erupted teeth without the use of antibiotic prophylaxis, from October 2016 to December 2018. Socket healing was assessed 3, 7, 21, and 60 days after exodontia and radiographs were obtained 7 and 60 days. On the SG, 87 exodontia were performed in 65 distinct surgical times, and on the CG, 76 exodontia in 36 surgical times. There were no complications of infectious origin in any group. The frequency of delay in alveolar epithelization at 21 days was higher in the SG (29.9% versus 3.9%, p &lt;0.001) and associated with a lower neutrophil count and wider HD time (p &lt;0.05). In the radiographic evaluation, density and complexity of the neoformed bone structure, measured by the intensity of pixels and fractal dimension, respectively, were lower in the SG (p &lt;0.001).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>We concluded that infectious complications are not common after exodontia in people with CKF undergoing HD, which does not support the systematic use of antibiotic prophylaxis in these patients. However, there is a delay in alveolar epithelization and a decrease in density and complexity of neoformed bone structures.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio/>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA013</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Bisphenol A effects on oral tissues and neoplastic cells behavior</Titulo>
		<Autores> Almeida TFA*, Oliveira SR, Campolina-Silva GH, Oliveira CA, Cardeal ZL, Diniz IMA, Leopoldino AM, Silva TA</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE MINAS GERAIS.</Universidade>
		<Email>tatifernandesalmeida@gmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>Bisphenol-A (BPA) is a monomer widely used in the production of thermal printer paper, water pipes, medical devices, food package, dental materials and others. It is a xenoestrogen that functions as an endocrine disruptor and is associated with several types of cancers. BPA was detected in a number of human fluids, including saliva. The effects of BPA in oral normal mucosa and neoplastic cells was not investigated yet. This study aimed to evaluate the effects of BPA in oral cells in vivo and in vitro and underlying mechanisms. We evaluated the oral mucosa and salivary glands of mice exposed to BPA (200 mg/L). The response of keratinocytes (NOK SI) and Head and Neck (HN) Squamous Cell Carcinoma (SCC), HN12 and HN13 cell lines to BPA was examined. We also investigated the BPA concentration in saliva of patients with oral SCC by chromatography. BPA exposure resulted in increase of oral mucosa epithelium thickness (jugal mucosa, stratum corneum and tongue) and a reduction in submandibular glands acini. In vitro BPA induced cell proliferation, angiogenesis, increased production of growth factors, metalloproteinases and proteins involved in cell survival as well the expression of α and β estrogen receptors (ER). The BPA effects were almost all abolished in the presence of ER antagonist. BPA also induced H3 histone acetylation. Saliva of patients with oral SCC showed an elevated concentration of BPA.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>BPA induces morphological changes in oral tissues and phenotypic and molecular alterations in keratinocytes and HNSCC cells through BPA-ER interaction and histone acetylation.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPEMIG/CAPES/CNPq</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA014</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Photoactivation of pericytes Nestin+ GFP/NG2+ DsRed in tissue repair</Titulo>
		<Autores> Valle IB*, Silva TA, Mesquita RA, Gomes NA, Barcelos LS, Menezes GB, Birbrair A, Diniz IMA</Autores>
		<Universidade>Clínica, Patologia e Cirurgia Odontológi - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DE MINAS GERAIS.</Universidade>
		<Email>isabellabdv@gmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>In this study, wound healing/tissue repair under the effect of photobiomodulation therapy (PBMT) was assessed in transgenic mice with intravital fluorescence [Nestin+ GFP(green)/NG2+ DsRed(red), undifferentiated cells - Nestin/pericytes - NG2]. Two contralateral full-thickness excisions that include the panniculus carnosus were performed with a 4 mm biopsy punch in 8-week-old mice (n=5) (CEUA 19/2018). A 0.5 mm thick silicone splint was then adapted to the wounds to prevent their early closure. Left side wound was photoactivated with diode laser (660nm, 20mW, 0.71 W/cm2, 7s) daily for 7 days. Right side was used as control. Next, an occlusive dressing was applied to prevent dehydration. Cell tracing was performed intravitally after 1h, 12h, 36h and 60h; and after 7 days on 15 μm sections by confocal microscopy. Blood perfusion using a Doppler imager was evaluated at 3 and 6 days. Wounds were measured after 2, 3, 4, 6 and 7 days. Histological analyzes were performed using hematoxylin/eosin staining at 7 days. Compared to the non-photoactivated control, pericyte tracing showed greater mobilization of cells in wounds treated by PBMT at times 1h, 12h, 60h and 7 days (p&lt;0.05). Doppler analysis showed increased blood perfusion in the photoactivated wounds than in the controls (p&lt;0.05). PBMT induced greater wound size reduction and more advanced stage of tissue repair in the wounds than the non-photoactivated controls (p&lt;0.05).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>PBMT remarkably accelerates tissue repair suggesting the direct participation of pericytes in the closure process of photoactivated wounds.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPs - FAPEMIG - 0100-18</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA015</Sigla>
		<Titulo>5-AZA inhibits cancer stem cell population in PTEN deficient oral squamous cell carcinoma</Titulo>
		<Autores> Borgato GB*, Borges GA, Squarize C, Souza AP, Castilho R</Autores>
		<Universidade>Biologia Buco-dental - FACULDADE DE ODONTOLOGIA DE PIRACICABA.</Universidade>
		<Email>gabriellborgato@hotmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>Oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) is a disease with a high capacity for tissue invasion, leading patients to a high degree of morbidity and unfavorable prognosis. PTEN is known for its negative regulation of the PI3K-AKT pathway, which may play a role in the maintenance of cancer stem cells. In addition, the association with the NF-κB signaling pathway can lead tumor proliferation and resistance to chemotherapeutic. Among the mechanisms studied in tumor formation and progression are the epigenetic alterations, like DNA methylation, which occurrence in the promoter region of tumor suppressor genes inhibits its expression. Here, we explored how demethylating agent 5-AZA can reduce an OSCC cell line aggressiveness and cancer stem cell population, using gene and protein expression, colony and tumorsphere formation, and ALDH/CD44 expression in flow cytometry. Intriguingly, 5-AZA upregulates NF-kB and AKT/PI3K pathways, however, decreases colony and tumorsphere formation. No changes in cancer stem cell population were observed. We verify how PTEN mRNA silencing also increased those pathways, enhancing colony and tumorsphere formation, and haven't changed the cancer stem cell population. We found that 5-AZA treatment in PTEN deficient OSCC cells downregulates NF-kB and didn't change the AKT/PI3K pathway, decreases colony and tumorsphere formation, also the cancer stem cell population.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Lastly, 5-AZA reduces the tumor aggressiveness and cancer stem cell population when the OSCC cells are PTEN deficient, and it can be a strategy to OSCC with PTEN loss of function.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: CAPES - 88881.132588/2016-01</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA016</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Cysteinyl leukotriene receptor antagonism modulates experimental periodontitis in rats</Titulo>
		<Autores> Moro MG*, Oliveira MDS, Jesus FN, Teixeira SA, Franco GCN, Spolidorio LC, Muscará MN, Holzhausen M</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - SÃO PAULO.</Universidade>
		<Email>marcellamoro@usp.br</Email>
		<Resumo>Cysteinyl leukotriene receptor activation is associated with the expression of proinflammatory molecules and osteoclastogenesis. The present study evaluated the effect of cysteinyl leukotriene receptor antagonism on experimental periodontitis induced by ligature in rats. One hundred and twenty male Wistar rats were randomly divided into four groups: Control - non-ligated group, ligature group (cotton ligature placed at lower first molars), and Montelukast (MT) group - ligature placed and systemic administration of two different doses of MT (10 or 30 mg/kg/day, MT 10 and MT 30, respectively). The amount of alveolar bone loss (ABL), as well as the histological analysis of collagen content, myeloperoxidase (MPO) activity, and gene expression of Collagen I, BLT1, CysLTR1, LTA4H, LTC4S, and bone metabolism and oxidative stress markers were determined at 7, 14 and 21 days. MT significantly reduced the expression of LTA4H, BLT1 and LTC4S (p&lt;0.05), and was effective in reducing ABL at 14 and 21 days (p&lt;0.05) with no significant effects on gingival collagen content and expression of oxidative stress markers (p&gt;0.05). MT significantly increased RUNX2 expression and decreased gingival MPO at 7 and 14 days (p&lt;0.05).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>It was concluded that leukotriene receptor antagonism by MT showed potential for modulating periodontitis progression.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio/>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA017</Sigla>
		<Titulo>MaR1/RvE1 improve regenerative-related activities of human periodontal ligament stem cells under Il-1β/TNF-α stimulus</Titulo>
		<Autores> Albuquerque-Souza E*, Holzhausen M, Harstuk H, Van Dyke TE, Kantarci A</Autores>
		<Universidade>Estomatologia - UNIVERSIDADE DE SÃO PAULO - SÃO PAULO.</Universidade>
		<Email>emanuelodonto_1988@hotmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>We evaluated the impact of maresin (MaR1) and resolvin (RvE1) in an inflammatory environment on human periodontal ligament stem cells (hPDLSCs), which were treated with MaR1(10nM) and/or RvE1(10nM) with or without IL-1β(10ng/mL) and/or TNF-α(10ng/mL) for 24h. Flow cytometry (FC) was used to evaluate stemness markers (CD45,CD11b,CD73,CD90,CD105,CDHLA-ABC,Oct-4,Sox-2). Cell proliferation (MTT assay), apoptosis activity (AnnexinV staining), and in vitro wound healing were also measured. Biomarkers of periodontal ligament regeneration [tenomodulin, α-SMA, and periostin] were analyzed by RT-qPCR, Immunofluorescesce, and FC. Phosphoproteomics was also performed. After osteogenic differentiation treatment, alizarin red staining was performed, alkaline phosphatase analyzed by ELISA, cemento-osteogenesis biomarkers (Runx2, Osteocalcin, CEMP1, CAP) by RT-qPCR and WB, and ChemR23 by FC. Overall, IL-1β/TNF-α stimulus reduced the stemness of hPDLSCs, the expression of regenerative biomarkers, impaired in vitro wound healing by inducing cell death, and decreased osteo-cementogenic activity. However, MaR1/RvE1 reverse this process partially rescuing biomarkers of stemness, ligament regeneration and cemento-osteogenesis and by inducing cell proliferation and reducing apoptosis. Such processes are related with the activation of different pathways through phosphorilation of different proteins.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>In summary, MaR1 and RvE1 are important denominators for regenerative activity of periodontal tissues lost to inflammatory milieu.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPs - Fapesp. - 2017/25260-6</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>HA018</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Xenograft combined with hyaluronic acid for the bone repair of critical size defects: a pre-clinical study in rats</Titulo>
		<Autores> Matheus HR*, Ervolino E, Gusman DJR, Alves BES, Araujo NJ, Fiorin LG, Pereira P, Almeida JM</Autores>
		<Universidade>Cirugia e Clínica Integrada - UNIVERSIDADE ESTADUAL PAULISTA - ARAÇATUBA.</Universidade>
		<Email>hrmatheus@hotmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effects of the combination of a xenograft and hyaluronic acid (HA) in different vehicles over bone repair in critical size defects (CSD). Fifteen male rats were divided in three experimental groups (n=5). The CSD (5mm) were made in the calvaria of all animals at day 0. Group Bio-Oss®: filled with Bio-Oss®; group Bio-Oss®/HA-LMW: filled with Bio-Oss® and hyaluronic acid in a vehicle of molecular weight (LMW) and low viscosity; group Bio-Oss®/HA/HMW: filled with Bio-Oss® and hyaluronic acid in a vehicle of high molecular weight (HMW) and high viscosity. Animals were euthanized 30 days postoperatively and the specimens were prepared for histologic, histometric of percentage of newly-formed bone (PNFB), histochemical and immunohistochemical (BMP2/4, OCN and TRAP) analyzes. Data were statistically analyzed (p ≤ 0.05). Higher PNFB was observed in Bio-Oss®/HA-HMW (23.68±1.89%) when compared with the other groups. The histologic analysis showed better tissue repair process when HA was used. Higher immunolabeling pattern was observed for both BMP2/4 and OCN in Bio-Oss®/HA-HMW when compared with Bio-Oss®. Bio-Oss® (5.8±3,27 cells) presented lower number of TRAP-positive cells when compared with the other groups. Lower percentage of mature collagen fibers was observed in Bio-Oss®/HA-HMW (20.59±2.48%) when compared with the other groups.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>It can be concluded that the combination of HA with Bio-Oss® improves bone repair, as well as the formulation of HA with high molecular weight and high viscosity increases PNFB within CSD.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio/>
	</Resumo>
</Resumos>
