<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Resumos xmlns:xsd="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>JL001</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Immunomodulatory effect of probiotics Lactobacillus rhammnosus and Lactobacillus acidophilus in human dendritic cells</Titulo>
		<Autores> Vale GC*, Suguimoto ESA, Ishikawa KH, Mayer MPA</Autores>
		<Universidade>Odontologia Restauradora - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO PIAUÍ.</Universidade>
		<Email>glauber@ufpi.edu.br</Email>
		<Resumo>Probiotics may modulate the immune response by altering maturation and function of antigen presenting cells, such as dendritic cells (DCs). This study explored the immunomodulatory properties of probiotics in DCs. Immature DCs were obtained from human cD14+ monocytes and challenged with <i>E. coli</i> LPS and/or probiotics lactobacilli (<i>L. rhammnosus </i>and <i>L. acidophilus</i>) at a ratio 1:10 (DC:bacteria). Relative transcription of cellular receptors and cytokines were assessed by RT-qPCR. Cytokines production was accessed by ELISA. Data were analyzed by ANOVA. LPS upregulated the expression of the receptors AIM2, NOD1 and NOD2, but downregulated NRLP3, TLR2 and TLR4 in human DCs, which expressed Cox-2, TNF-a, IL-1β, IL-6, IL-8, IL-12 and IL-18, differing from the immature DCs. Exposure to probiotics resulted in downregulation of the expression most tested genes encoding receptors and inflammatory mediators when compared to negative control and LPS- induced mature DCs. Furthermore, intra and extracellular receptors encoding genes were downregulated in probiotics infected DCs challenged with LPS, and these cells presented increased Cox2, IL-6, IL8 and IL10, but decreased IL-12 mRNA levels when compared to LPS challenged cells. Protein levels indicated that LPS challenged DCs infected with<i> L. acidophilus</i> presented the highest levels of IL-1β and TNFα in cells supernatant compared to the other groups.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Our data indicated that the tested probiotics can interfere in DCs function by altering the expression of receptors and inflammatory mediators in distinct ways.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPs - Fapesp - 2017/10829-3, 2015/18273-9</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>JL002</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Influence of immunoglobulins on plaque and gingival indices in children with and without Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</Titulo>
		<Autores> Ribeiro TR*, Martins RARC, Santos CF, Silva SM, Silva PGB, Costa FWG, Forti AC, Fonteles CSR</Autores>
		<Universidade>Clínica Odontológica - UNIVERSIDADE FEDERAL DO CEARÁ.</Universidade>
		<Email>thyciana_odonto@yahoo.com.br</Email>
		<Resumo>This study aimed to evaluate the association between salivary immunoglobulins, plaque index (PI) and gingival index (GI) in children with (CDM1) and without (SDM1) type 1 diabetes mellitus. The CDM1 group had 38 children and an equal number of volunteers, matched by sex and age were recruited as controls (n=38, SDM1). Clinical examination was performed for PI and GI evaluation. Non-stimulated whole saliva was collected, enzyme inhibitor was added, saliva was centrifuged, supernatant was separated and stored at -80°C. Concentrations of immunoglobulins A (IgA), G (IgG) and M (IgM) were determined by ELISA test. Data were tested by the Kolmogorov-Smirnov, Mann-Whitney and Spearman's tests. Variables correlated with immunoglobulins were included in a multiple linear regression model (p &lt; 0.05). Gingival index was higher in SDM1 (CDM1: 0.16 ± 0.17; SDM1: 0.24 ± 0.23, p = 0.040). In CDM1, there was a correlation between IgA and age (rho = 0.371, p = 0.024), IgM and IgG (rho = 0.459, p = 0.007), IgM and IG (rho = 0.394, p = 0.014). In CDM1, multiple linear regression showed that age (p = 0.041; β = 0.363), gingival (p = 0.041; β = 0.398) and plaque (p = 0.008; β = -0.506) indexes were good predictors of IgA levels in saliva; however, these variables were not good predictors of IgM or IgG levels in this population. In SDM1, age was the only variable that significantly predicted IgA (p &lt; 0.001; β = 0.677) and IgM (p &lt; 0.001; β = 0.570).</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>In conclusion, IgA was associated with plaque and gingival indexes in diabetic children, but this association was not observed among non-diabetic patients.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: CNPq - 445591/2014-5</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
	<Resumo>
		<Sigla>JL003</Sigla>
		<Titulo>Possible role of alendronate induced bone and gingival tissue alterations in bisphosphonate related osteonecrosis of the jaws</Titulo>
		<Autores> Giro G*, Watinaga SE, Savedra LFA, Vilela A, Rodrigues IV, Santos MGB, Frigo L</Autores>
		<Universidade>Ceppe Centro de Pós Graduação e Pesquisa - UNIVERSIDADE GUARULHOS.</Universidade>
		<Email>gabi.giro@gmail.com</Email>
		<Resumo>This study aimed to evaluate possible changes in mandible and gingival tissue in patients under oral bisphosphonate treatment and to investigate the relationship between these changes and medication related osteonecrosis of the jaws (MR-ONJ) etiology. Therefore, 30 postmenopausal subjects, candidates to implant supported restorations were enrolled in this study. These subjects were divided into 2 groups: the control group (subjects without clinical diagnosis of osteoporosis and who did not use any kind of medication to bone mass loss prevention) and the alendronate group (subjects under alendronate therapy for at least one year). The subjects were submitted to dental implants placement and bone samples measuring 2 mm in diameter were collected for histological and immunohistochemical evaluations. In addition, a venous blood sample was collected of each subject for quantification of bone remodeling biomarkers. After implant osseointegration, samples of gingival tissue were obtained to evaluate the quality of the gingival tissue presented by both groups. The alendronate group presented lower rates of bone remodeling biomarkers, a decrease in the number of viable osteocytes and a lack in the organization integrity of the collagen fibers presented in bone and gingiva.</Resumo>
		<Conclusao>Within the limitations of this study, the results suggested that alterations observed in the alendronate group may interfere in the viability of the bone tissue. The epithelial fragility could lead to a break down in immune response to oral pathogens, contributing to the etiology of MR- ONJ.</Conclusao>
		<Apoio>Apoio: FAPs - Fapesp - 2014/25228-7</Apoio>
	</Resumo>
</Resumos>
